<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Hugo Roy</title>
	<atom:link href="http://hugoroy.eu/feed.rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>http://hugoroy.eu/</link>
	<description>Hugo Roy's weblog</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2013 18:05:42 +0200</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>daily</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
		<!--item>
			<title></title>
			<link></link>
			<pubDate>Wed Nov 14 14:00:00 +0200 2013</pubDate>
			<dc:creator></dc:creator>

                </item>     -->
        <item>
            <title>Patent fees are not like property tax</title>
            <link>http://hroy.eu/posts/patent-fees-property-tax/</link>
            <pubDate>2013-09-21T13:32:43Z</pubDate>
            <dc:creator>Hugo Roy</dc:creator>
                <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 id="thinking-of-patents-as-property">Thinking of patents as property?</h2>
                              <p>There’s a constant debate when it comes to patents and copyright laws. Do they fit in a general category of property rights? Are they like property at all? [[!toggle id=&quot;rms-cr&quot; text=&quot;[+]&quot;]]</p>
                              <p>[[!toggleable id=&quot;rms-cr&quot; text=&quot;&quot;&quot; I can’t hide that my opinion has been influenced by the writings of Richard Stallman, who’s been challenging the status quo for over two decades. I’ve summarised in French some of <a href="https://pinboard.in/u:hugoroy/t:richard_stallman/t:copyright/">his publications on the subject</a>. [[!toggle id=&quot;rms-cr&quot; text=&quot;[hide]&quot;]]&quot;&quot;&quot;]]</p>
                              <p>Current developments in patent law, especially in the US, have given rise to concerns about the harm they might do to innovation which they seek to guide incentives. This has been more than obvious in the case of software and patent trolls.</p>
                              <p>Some people, instead of fixing what’s inherently wrong with patents, are trying to find some minor fixes. Recently it has been <a href="http://ssrn.com/abstract=2318521">proposed</a> to make the patent fees vary depending on how much the patent is “practised” by the holder.</p>
                              <p>I stumbled upon this article (which might be a good idea, although I think it misses the larger picture) while reading <a href="http://www.patentlyo.com/patent/2013/09/raising-maintenance-fees-for-non-practiced-inventions.html">patentlyo this afternoon</a>:</p>
                              <blockquote>
                              <p>Post-grant patent maintenance fees offer an easy mechanism for shifting patentee behavior. In the US, patent holders must pay a maintenance fee three times during the life of an issued patent. I <strong>think of the fee as akin to property tax.</strong> When a real-property owner fails to pay the property taxes, the state forecloses. In the patent system failure to pay the maintenance fees similarly results in the property right be taken from the non-payer.</p>
                              </blockquote>
                              <p>I couldn’t resist to take this opportunity to give a small excerpt of how little value I think this analogy to property bears with thinking about patents.</p>
                              <p>Earlier this year, I attended a small seminar on “comparative perspectives of patent laws” which introduced itself with some American literature on general theories of property. [[!toggle id=&quot;comp-persp&quot; text=&quot;[+]&quot;]]</p>
                              <p>[[!toggleable id=&quot;comp-persp&quot; text=&quot;&quot;&quot; Apart from the criticism that follows, I have to say it was a very interesting seminar and comparative legal studies are often good ways to self-questioning one’s views. The introduction also featured Barry Field, “the Evolution of Property Rights” (1989) worth reading as a whole for explaining patterns of emergence of property rights, but maybe also for the historical account of UK patent hero James Watt. [[!toggle id=&quot;comp-persp&quot; text=&quot;[hide]&quot;]]&quot;&quot;&quot;]]</p>
                              <p>We were given to read Harold Demsetz, “Toward a Theory of Property Rights” (1967). This is not the only attempt at trying a general theory of property law that encompass patents and copyright. But this one is interesting for some of the analysis it brings regarding the interaction of individuals, the law, and the State; which is at the centre of patentlyo’s thinking of patent fees akin to property taxes.</p>
                              <p>In this theory, patent laws aim at modifying behaviour by internalising externalities. Yes, this is an economic theory… Later in the text, about the concept and role of property rights, the author outlines two ways for enrolling people in the military. In the first one, where people are free to join or not, the State tries to buy people in with providing for education, salaries, etc. In the second one, people are drafted by default, so they can only buy a way out of the army. For the author, there’s a kind of dynamic from no-property to property, once we have a system that creates benefit of internalising that’s higher than the cost of excluding people of the benefit. (In the second system, the State gets all the benefit).</p>
                              <h2 id="property-and-rights">Property and rights</h2>
                              <p>This thinking in terms of property theory is nonsense to me, just like saying the patent fees are akin to property tax. What’s the connection exactly? Is anything the State is creating a tax for to be understood in terms of a property logic? Then, I’ll say that the patent fees are like the tax on cigarettes. Just like taxing cigarettes try to discourage people from smoking, the patent fees try to discourage the patent holders from keeping on their patents too long instead of unleashing the benefits of the invention to everyone.</p>
                              <p>That’s absurd, just as absurd as Demsetz’s theory of thinking as military drafting in terms of property. Who’s owning what exactly? When I was trying to answer that question while reading Demsetz, my conclusion was that Demsetz thought of a property right in owning oneself. But you don’t “own yourself” in the sense that most people give meaning to the verb owning. You are free to do things, you are responsible for your actions.</p>
                              <p>There’s some kind of confusion between having the freedom to do something that impacts other people, and having a right of property on something. It’s usually much more helpful to think in terms of rights and freedoms in general and try to think what’s the subject/object of a “right”. [[!toggle id=&quot;kant-rechts&quot; text=&quot;[+]&quot;]]</p>
                              <p>[[!toggleable id=&quot;kant-rechts&quot; text=&quot;&quot;&quot; If you don’t know what I mean here, because this is just a blog post and I’m not thinking it through, I’m trying to draw from the distinction made by Kant between personal rights and “real rights” (I’m not even sure this is how it’s translated in English). [[!toggle id=&quot;kant-rechts&quot; text=&quot;[hide]&quot;]]&quot;&quot;&quot;]]</p>
                              <p>This is to me the original flaw that’s also inherent to thinking of patent fees akin to property tax; not acknowledgeing the fundamental difference between the objects of a right (a <em>patentable</em> invention, a house) for which there are rights as such (a patent, a property right).</p>
                              <p>The patent fees do not serve the same purpose as the property tax. The first one is a reminder that patents are privileges granted by the State in exchange for everyone else's freedom to use the patented invention; while the property tax is not designed to put an end to the property right when it is too costly for society's benefit.</p>
                              <p>Thinking of patent law in terms of property brings confusion.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
        <title>Time to stop talking about the free/open Internet?</title>
        <link>http://hroy.eu/posts/free+open_internet/</link>
        <pubDate>2013-09-20T17:35:15Z</pubDate>
        <dc:creator>Hugo Roy</dc:creator>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h1 id="time-to-stop-talking-about-the-freeopen-internet">Time to stop talking about the free/open Internet?</h1>
                                  <p>Last week, instead of working on the bar exams, I spent some time on Twitter discussing with Ryan Heath, spokesperson for EU Commissioner Neelie Kroes who's pushing for a new law on telecommunications. The draft is drawing some criticism right now, as it's said to defeat network neutrality (Bits of Freedom points out that the current draft could be <a href="https://twitter.com/bitsoffreedom/status/377882941122027520">incompatible with the Dutch law on network neutrality</a>).</p>
                                  <p>But I wasn't interested in the discussions on the bill itself, rather I saw that Ryan Heath claimed to “♥ open internet” on Twitter and so it <a href="https://twitter.com/hugoroyd/status/377880421859475456">triggered my curiosity</a>. What does “free/open internet” mean for a EU commissioner spokesperson? So here's what he wrote:</p>
                                  <blockquote>
                                  <p>“open Internet” means a network everyone can access affordably and without restrictions on content, with room to innovate</p>
                                  </blockquote>
                                  <p>When I asked what he meant exactly by no restrictions on content, he <a href="https://twitter.com/RyanHeathEU/status/377883015470653441">replied</a>:</p>
                                  <blockquote>
                                  <p>Zero restrictions essentially. Of course not extending 2 content such as child pornography(punishable as serious criminal offence)</p>
                                  </blockquote>
                                  <p>(I have to say it's amazing for a spokesperson that he was able to contradict himself in less than 140 characters.)</p>
                                  <p>I think this illustrates that the term open internet is to be avoided. It is clearly meaningless and does nothing to help frame the discussion.</p>
                                  <p>So I think I’ll add this to my list of buzzwords that I try to avoid: Cloud computing, Big Data, Open Web, (add yours).</p>
                                  <hr>
                                  <p>On a side note, the argument of the EU Commission spokesperson that evenining was: if you fight against us on this, that means you're against enabling <a href="https://twitter.com/RyanHeathEU/status/377873152787099648">internet-innovation for hospitals</a>. Because you know, if your hospital does not have the right surgeon, <a href="https://twitter.com/RyanHeathEU/status/378196072856043521">there’s an app for that…</a></p>
                                  <p>This kind of thinking must be avoided. Laws that regulate internet intermediaries should not be made solely on the basis of market regulation; because the internet is an important infrastructure for all of us, it's more importantly a matter of freedom and human rights.</p>
                                  <p>BTW, if you apply that market approach to the examples of hospitals in need of prioritized internet access, that also implies that you allow telecoms to <a href="https://twitter.com/RyanHeathEU/status/377873152787099648">charge hospitals more money</a> for the privilege of prioritized access. Well done.</p>
                                  <hr>
                                  <p>PS: I’ve always disliked the expression “open Web.” Not so much because I prefer the term Free Software over Open Source because it refers to freedom, which I think is more important and less ambiguous than “open” but also because the expression itself implies that there is such a thing as a “closed Web.” Then, what would that be? A website with Flash? I don't even consider flash as part of the web, but just some proprietary blobs served over http. I don't think that everything served over http is necessarily part of the web.</p>
                                  <p>[[!tag lang:en nonsense]]</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
        <title>Here’s why economists hate software patents</title>
        <link>http://identi.ca/hugoroy/note/8zgqhZC8TiOU4Lu6EZSdlg</link>
        <dc:creator>Hugo Roy</dc:creator>
        <pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2013 18:05:42 +0200</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
        <title>Vim Tip: arrow keys</title>
        <link>http://hugoroy.eu/blog/vim-tip-make-arrows-behave-in-vim-like-in-a-gui-text-editor.html</link>
        <pubDate>2013-06-20</pubDate>
        <dc:creator>Hugo Roy</dc:creator>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h1 id="make-arrows-behave-in-vim-like-in-a-gui-text-editor">Make arrows behave in VIM like in a GUI text editor</h1>
                                  <p>This is wholly heretic to VIM purists, but I find it very useful for people who do use ↑ and ↓ keys and do not intend to use them as a replacement for k and j. Just add in your <a
                                  href="https://github.com/hugoroy/.vim/blob/master/vimrc">~/.vimrc</a>:</p>
                                  <script src="https://gist.github.com/hugoroy/5822226.js"></script>
                                  <noscript><pre>
                                  " make arrows behave like gui text editor
                                  nnoremap &lt;up&gt; gk
                                  nnoremap &lt;down&gt; gj
                                  inoremap &lt;up&gt; &lt;C-O&gt;gk
                                  inoremap &lt;down&gt; &lt;C-O&gt;gj
                                  vnoremap &lt;up&gt; gk
                                  vnoremap &lt;down&gt; gj
                                  </pre>
                                  <a
                                  href="https://gist.github.com/hugoroy/5822226/raw/4e947e54558ad416cd9abc3290ee651d07a80a12/arrows.vimrc">most updated version on github</a>
                                  </noscript>
                                  ]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
        <title>ToS;DR in Action: “What is yours stays yours”, ORLY?</title>
        <link>http://tosdr.org/blog/tosdr-in-action-owned.html</link>
        <pubDate>2013-06-17</pubDate>
        <dc:creator>Hugo Roy</dc:creator>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h1 id="what-is-yours-stays-yours-oh-really">“What is yours stays yours”: Oh, really?</h1>
                                  <p>[This post is part of a series in collaboration with the BBC Radio 4 “Law in Action,” where we try to debunk some of the myths related to terms of service and privacy policies. <a href="http://tosdr.org/blog/tosdr-in-action-i-have-read-and-agree.html">Read episode 1</a>]</p>
                                  <p>This week, we're focusing on another big topic related to terms of service: what's happening to content (e.g. pictures, videos) you upload to a service?</p>
                                  <p>Services usually mention that they're not going to sell your content or that “what's yours stays yours.” Yet, you'd better be careful: there are still many things they could do…</p>
                                  <h2 id="a-very-basic-introduction-to-copyright-and-authors-rights">A (very) basic introduction to copyright and author's rights</h2>
                                  <p>The basic principle is that once a person has created or invested in a work, usually with a minimum of creativity, this person is automatically considered the “author” or the copyright holder of that published work. There are differences around the world, but we can say it's a basic principle under the Berne convention, an international agreement that governs copyright and author's rights laws worldwide.</p>
                                  <p>Such laws bear various justifications: allowing to reward creators for their work and incentivise their production; organising exclusive rights to enable return-on-investments; enhancing creativity to bring benefits to society at large.</p>
                                  <p>If, nowadays, copyright has been discussed at great lengths in politics and the media as a burning issue concerning non-authorised distribution of music and films on the Internet, another significant side of copyright has been mainly overlooked: what's happening to <strong>your</strong> copyright, the rights on your photos, your videos, etc.</p>
                                  <h2 id="how-services-exploit-your-copyright">How services exploit your copyright</h2>
                                  <p>Today, incredibly vast amounts of copyrighted works are published by users on the Web (in the so-called Web 2.0 era of “User Generated Content”) through publication services such as Twitter, Facebook, YouTube, Instagram, and etc. However, very little has been said about what happens to users' copyrights. The sad truth is written plainly in the Terms: a lot of services are claiming over-broad rights on users' content – while they have absolutely not contributed to its creation!</p>
                                  <ul>
                                  <li><p>True, with these services, “you retain your rights” to your content. They do not ask for a transfer of copyright ownership, but they mainly ask you to grant them <strong>broad</strong>, sometimes <strong>almost-unlimited</strong>, licenses to your content.</p></li>
                                  <li><p>True, these services do not “sell” your content. What they do is <em>transfer</em> the license you grant them, or they grant <em>sublicenses</em> themselves to third-parties. That means they can give rights on your content to other businesses, without asking you.</p></li>
                                  <li><p>True, users have “agreed” to that. But we know that the current agreement to terms of service is <a href="http://tosdr.org/blog/tosdr-in-action-i-have-read-and-agree.html">meaningless</a>, and moreover, for many services (Twitter, Facebook, Instagram, Twitpic, and etc.), the current copyright license was created when the terms were changed.</p></li>
                                  </ul>
                                  <p><a href="http://tosdr.org/#twitter">Twitter</a> can change the terms at any time when they see fit; they can choose to give notification, in their sole discretion, via an @Twitter update or via email. In September 2009, Twitter considerably changed the terms for the copyright license and only gave a very short notice a few hours before the changes applied. Furthermore, if you actually try to go read that email and the blog post it links to, you will notice that Twitter omits to mention the biggest changes to their copyright license. [See our discussion: <a href="https://groups.google.com/d/msg/tosdr/-B4iO-9xHvg/0yoWGoEISrEJ">on the mailing-list</a>]</p>
                                  <p><a href="http://tosdr.org/#twitpic">Twitpic</a> has been able to exploit the rights users have granted them, probably without most users knowing. For instance, when Twitpic realised they could make money off their users' pictures, they <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/technology-13372982">changed the copyright license</a> to make a deal with media agency WENN.</p>
                                  <p>When <a href="http://tosdr.org/#instagram">Instagram</a> was bought by Facebook, they only had a limited copyright license that was neither transferable nor sublicensable. At this stage, although Facebook had bought the company Instagram for $1 billion, Facebook could not really benefit from the rights over users' photos. Guess what. When Instagram changed their terms in January this year, they aligned their copyright license to Facebook's (among <a href="http://www.slate.com/blogs/future_tense/2012/12/19/instagram_privacy_everyone_s_ignoring_the_real_problems_with_its_terms_of.html">other issues</a>).</p>
                                  <p>Before January 19, 2013, this is what Instagram wrote about copyright in their terms:</p>
                                  <blockquote>
                                  <p>Proprietary Rights in Content on Instagram</p>
                                  <ol type="1">
                                  <li>Instagram does NOT claim ANY ownership rights in the text, files, images, photos, video, sounds, musical works, works of authorship, applications, or any other materials (collectively, &quot;Content&quot;) that you post on or through the Instagram Services. By displaying or publishing (&quot;posting&quot;) any Content on or through the Instagram Services, you hereby grant to Instagram a non-exclusive, fully paid and royalty-free, worldwide, limited license to use, modify, delete from, add to, publicly perform, publicly display, reproduce and translate such Content, including without limitation distributing part or all of the Site in any media formats through any media channels, except Content not shared publicly (&quot;private&quot;) will not be distributed outside the Instagram Services.</li>
                                  </ol>
                                  </blockquote>
                                  <p>After January 19, 2013:</p>
                                  <blockquote>
                                  <p>Rights</p>
                                  <ol type="1">
                                  <li>Instagram does not claim ownership of any Content that you post on or through the Service. Instead, <em>you hereby grant to Instagram a non-exclusive, fully paid and royalty-free,</em> <strong>transferable, sub-licensable,</strong> <em>worldwide license to use the Content that you post on or through the Service,</em> subject to the Service's Privacy Policy, available here http://instagram.com/legal/privacy/, including but not limited to sections 3 (&quot;Sharing of Your Information&quot;), 4 (&quot;How We Store Your Information&quot;), and 5 (&quot;Your Choices About Your Information&quot;). You can choose who can view your Content and activities, including your photos, as described in the Privacy Policy.</li>
                                  </ol>
                                  </blockquote>
                                  <p>Facebook's current terms:</p>
                                  <blockquote>
                                  <ol start="2" type="1">
                                  <li>Sharing Your Content and Information</li>
                                  </ol>
                                  <p>You own all of the content and information you post on Facebook, and you can control how it is shared through your privacy and application settings. In addition:</p>
                                  <ol type="1">
                                  <li>For content that is covered by intellectual property rights, like photos and videos (IP content), you specifically give us the following permission, subject to your privacy and application settings: <em>you grant us a non-exclusive,</em> <strong>transferable, sub-licensable,</strong> <em>royalty-free, worldwide license to use any IP content that you post on or in connection with Facebook</em> (IP License).* This IP License ends when you delete your IP content or your account unless your content has been shared with others, and they have not deleted it.</li>
                                  </ol>
                                  </blockquote>
                                  <p>(Do not hesitate to have a look back at Facebook's <a href="http://consumerist.com/2009/02/15/facebooks-new-terms-of-service-we-can-do-anything-we-want-with-your-content-forever/">previous copyright licenses</a>)</p>
                                  <h2 id="but-this-is-necessary-for-them-right">But, this is necessary for them, right?</h2>
                                  <p>I have seen some arguments stating that these copyright licenses are “boilerplate” (implying they're everywhere), and that they're really necessary for them to provide you with the features of the service.</p>
                                  <p>But this is not true. First, these copyright licenses are far from standard because there are some vast differences even between similar services. You can see that there are a wide variety of licenses with huge differences that we have <a href="http://tosdr.org/topics.html#copyright-scope">scrutinized</a>.</p>
                                  <p>For instance, the copyright license you grant to <a href="http://tosdr.org/#youtube">YouTube</a> bears no explicit limitation, whereas <a href="http://tosdr.org/#vimeo">Vimeo</a>'s copyright license is explicitly limited to 4 purposes. In addition, the copyright license you grant to Vimeo is neither transferable nor sublicensable, as opposed to YouTube.</p>
                                  <p>To take another example, you can compare the copyright license that <a href="http://tosdr.org/#twitter">Twitter</a> requires with the license for <a href="http://tosdr.org/#identi-ca">Identi.ca</a> or <a href="http://tosdr.org/#seenthis">SeenThis</a>. In case this isn't significant enough, you can also compare Twitter's current copyright license with the copyright license they had <a href="https://twitter.com/tos/previous">before 2009</a>.</p>
                                  <p>Secondly, if it were really necessary for these services to have such broad copyright licenses, I still see no clear reason why they would ask for the possibility to <em>transfer</em> or to <em>sublicense</em> them.</p>
                                  <p>And even if it was a matter of necessity, services could just state it clearly and expressly in the copyright licenses. For instance, <a href="http://tosdr.org/#soundcloud">SoundCloud</a> asks for a copyright license like this:</p>
                                  <blockquote>
                                  <p><strong>To the extent it is necessary</strong> in order for SoundCloud to provide you with any of the aforementioned hosting services, to undertake any of the tasks set forth in these Terms of Use and/or to enable your use of the Platform, you hereby grant such licences to SoundCloud on a <strong>limited</strong>, worldwide, non-exclusive, royalty-free and fully paid basis. <a href="https://groups.google.com/d/topic/tosdr/_gI8wQ3PZ2M/discussion">Source</a></p>
                                  </blockquote>
                                  <h2 id="which-terms-of-service-are-fair">Which terms of service are fair?</h2>
                                  <p>Do not get fooled. Some businesses <em>do</em> get broad rights on your published content when you “accept” their terms of service. Your content is valuable, you should not blindly accept copyright licenses over them.</p>
                                  <p>Here at ToS;DR, we <em>systematically</em> check the copyright licenses carried in terms of service to find broad language. If you want to avoid giving away your rights, one simple first step can be to <a href="http://tosdr.org/downloads.html">download</a> our web browser extension and instantly check the information regarding the copyright licenses of services you use.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
        <title>ToS;DR in Action: “I have read and agree to the terms”</title>
        <link>http://tosdr.org/blog/tosdr-in-action-i-have-read-and-agree.html</link>
        <pubDate>2013-06-10</pubDate>
        <dc:creator>Hugo Roy</dc:creator>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h1 id="tosdr-in-action">ToS;DR in Action</h1>
                                  <p>During the month of June, the ToS;DR team is collaborating with the BBC on their <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b006tgy1" title="BBC Radio 4Law in Action">“Law in action” programme</a> for a 4-show series dedicated to the <a href="http://tosdr.org/topics.html" title="Topics covered by ToS;DR">topics</a> of terms of service and privacy policies.</p>
                                  <p>On June 4, <a href="http://www.rozenberg.net/">Joshua Rozenberg</a>, Julia Hörnle from Queen Mary University, Jimm, and I talked about what is the probably most unavoidable topic when it comes to terms of service. You can already listen to the <a href="http://downloads.bbc.co.uk/podcasts/radio4/law/rss.xml">podcast</a> on the BBC site. Stay tuned for the next topics, on each Tuesday at 4 pm UK time.</p>
                                  <h2 id="i-have-read-and-agree-to-the-terms-why-is-that-what-we-call-the-biggest-lie-on-the-web">“I have read and agree to the terms”: Why is that what we call the biggest lie on the Web?</h2>
                                  <p>See at 0m53s. <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=lbvwZ4LWeEc&amp;t=0m53s">Video: Eddie Izzard on how iTunes terms change all the time</a></p>
                                  <p>This is a sensitive topic, and it boils down to consent. Consent is a pretty common condition to form binding agreements around the world, but what is it exactly? Clicking “I agree to the terms” or checking that little box: what are the implications?</p>
                                  <p>First, there's absolutely no denying that in its current state, the terms of service acceptance mechanism is deeply broken, for two obvious reasons:</p>
                                  <ul>
                                  <li><p>the terms of service and privacy policies are <em>too long</em> and often do not provide shorter versions, nor do they provide <em>plain-English</em> versions either;</p></li>
                                  <li><p>the average user signs up to lots and lots of online services, sometimes agreeing to multiple documents or services at once because of <a href="http://tosdr.org/topics.html#third" title="ToS;DR about third parties in terms">third parties</a> that can be involved.</p></li>
                                  </ul>
                                  <p>In 2008, <a href="http://lorrie.cranor.org/#publications">Lorrie Cranor</a> from Carnegie Mellon estimated that it would take 244 hours every year for each individual to read the privacy policies they agree to online. (<a href="http://www.theatlantic.com/technology/archive/2012/03/reading-the-privacy-policies-you-encounter-in-a-year-would-take-76-work-days/253851/">The Atantic: 76 work days to read all the terms</a>).</p>
                                  <figure>
                                  <img src="tosdr-in-action-i-have-read-and-agree/books.jpg" title="UK consumer org “Which?” comparing lenghts" alt="From http://conversation.which.co.uk/technology/length-of-website-terms-and-conditions/"><figcaption>From http://conversation.which.co.uk/technology/length-of-website-terms-and-conditions/</figcaption>
                                  </figure>
                                  <p>Second, these two problems are multiplied by the facts that:</p>
                                  <ul>
                                  <li><p>terms of service and privacy policies change <em>all the time</em> and it's very, very hard to keep track of all of them (although we're trying really hard to solve this by building <a href="http://tosdr.github.io/ToSBack3" title="ToSBack3 is currently in development">ToSBack</a>)</p></li>
                                  <li><p>some services, including major ones, do not even commit to a legal obligation of notifying their users of such changes.</p></li>
                                  </ul>
                                  <p>Since 2007, Facebook has brought major changes to their longer-than-the-US-Constitution-terms-of-service about <a href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2010/04/facebook-timeline" title="EFF: Facebook terms, a timeline">every year</a>. Among the services that do not make it an obligation to notify users of changes: Microsoft, Yahoo!, Skype, Amazon, YouTube.</p>
                                  <p>(Ironically, it seems that the Yahoo! privacy policy has been changed to now make it an obligation to notify users of modifications; however, I do not remember having received notification of this change, although this is the kind of email I pay attention to for ToS;DR. Anyway, I'll have to update <a href="http://tosdr.org/#yahoo">#yahoo</a>).</p>
                                  <p><a href="http://www.apple.com/legal/internet-services/itunes/us/terms.html">Apple iTunes US terms state</a>:</p>
                                  <blockquote>
                                  <p>Apple reserves the right at any time to modify this Agreement and to impose new or additional terms or conditions on your use of the iTunes Service. Such modifications and additional terms and conditions will be effective immediately and incorporated into this Agreement. Your continued use of the iTunes Service will be deemed acceptance thereof.</p>
                                  </blockquote>
                                  <figure>
                                  <img src="tosdr-in-action-i-have-read-and-agree/itunes-agree.jpg" title="Do you agree?" alt="Screenshot of iTunes ToS"><figcaption>Screenshot of iTunes ToS</figcaption>
                                  </figure>
                                  <h2 id="but-are-long-tos-legal-is-it-enforceable">But are long ToS legal, is it enforceable?</h2>
                                  <p>Before answering these questions, we need to stop for a minute.</p>
                                  <ul>
                                  <li><p>Courts in different jurisdictions under different laws may come to different conclusions regarding these practices, especially about whether changing terms without notifying users is acceptable or not.</p></li>
                                  <li><p>Just because you live in a society that is usually more protective about your rights, it does not mean you're safe, because a lot of the terms of service have <a href="http://tosdr.org/topics.html#jurisdiction-law">choice of law clauses</a></p></li>
                                  <li><p>Even when such practices would be deemed illegal, it does not mean that they are not doing any harm. Quite on the contrary, if you've got to go see a judge (i.e., taking the burden of litigation on you in time and/or money) it probably means that harm's been done already. Good contracts do not provoke litigation; they ease private relationships.</p></li>
                                  <li><p>And sometimes, even when companies have been fined for practices that have been considered illegal, they have still succeeded in profiting from their actions.</p></li>
                                  </ul>
                                  <p>Julia Hörnle put it nicely on the show: “They're getting away with it.”</p>
                                  <p>Now, about terms that can change without notification to you, I suppose they are valid in the US, but they're usually not valid in Europe (which does not prevent companies providing services in Europe to have such clauses in their terms and to continue not to notify users…).</p>
                                  <p>For those interested, there are interesting cases in the UK:</p>
                                  <ul>
                                  <li>Parker v. South Eastern Railway Company (1877)</li>
                                  <li>Thornton v. Shoe Lane Parking (1970)</li>
                                  </ul>
                                  <p>In France, consent is part of the four conditions necessary to be forming a valid contract (article 1108 of the Code Civil). The question is then if the terms of service on websites can be considered &quot;reasonable notice&quot;, and thus be enforceable to the user that has agreed to them. A <a href="http://www.legalis.net/spip.php?page=jurisprudence-decision&amp;id_article=3534">recent French supreme court decision</a> implies that the acceptance of ToS requires notified consent; merely hosting the ToS online does not create a contractual obligation.</p>
                                  <p>There was also an <a href="http://www.mondaq.com/canada/x/241354/Terms+of+Service+and+Deceased+Users+Account">interesting case in Canada</a> in which the heirs of a deceased person wanted access and ownership of their brother's email account at Yahoo. One of the questions was around: were the changes to the terms reasonably communicated to the user?</p>
                                  <p>In the European Commission's new data protection regulation currently under review by the European Parliament and the European Council, there's a proposal that the burden of proof of consent be on the service provider.</p>
                                  <p>And that gets me to my last point about consent. In the end, I still have no clear idea what consent actually means in the reality of online services today.</p>
                                  <p>While we have the personal data 1995 directive in the European Union, it seems that there's no enforced consensus at this point about what actually constitutes consent to personal data processing. On the one hand, data protection authorities want to promote interpretations that are in favour or users' privacy. On the other hand, I don't see much happening on how services deal with their users' consent. Let's hope the next regulation will clarify that, and hopefully, not result in less protection or in meaningless consent (see for instance the intense lobbying over the proposed requirement that consent be expressed consent).</p>
                                  <figure>
                                  <img src="tosdr-in-action-i-have-read-and-agree/eudatap.jpg" title="Data protection logo"><figcaption></figcaption>
                                  </figure>
                                  <p>Oh, I forgot to answer the question. No, some of these terms are actually illegal:</p>
                                  <ul>
                                  <li><p><a href="http://www.wired.co.uk/news/archive/2013-01/29/whatsapp-privacy">WhatsApp breached data privacy laws by storing non-user contact details</a></p></li>
                                  <li><p><a href="http://www.onlinelaw.de/de/aktuelles/it_news.php?we_objectID=324&amp;pid=0">German Court rules Facebook original Friendfinder and various terms and conditions to be illegal (Landgericht Berlin, Urteil vom 6. März 2012, Az. 16 O 551/10)</a></p></li>
                                  <li><p><a href="http://www.bloomberg.com/news/2013-05-07/apple-s-customer-data-privacy-rules-struck-down-by-german-court.html">Apple’s Customer Data-Privacy Rules Struck Down by German Court</a></p></li>
                                  </ul>
                                  <hr>
                                  <p>So, right now, it's fair to assume that if you clicked &quot;I agree&quot; that means you consent presumably to what's written in the terms; even if that involves <a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2010/04/17/gamestation-grabs-souls-o_n_541549.html" title="It happened on April 1">selling your soul</a>.</p>
                                  <p>What's problematic is that although terms of service are kinds of non-negotiated contracts, they're still a two-way relationship. There are meaningful things written in there, about your rights and obligations as well, to which you presumably consent.</p>
                                  <p>Every once in a while, when a service brings major changes to their terms, we see some media coverage and sometimes outrage at what services can do or aim to do with our personal data or with our creative content. So, we can assume that <em>people do care</em> about these issues; yet, the I-agree-to-the-terms-circus goes on and on.</p>
                                  <p>My assumption then, is that when we discuss privacy and surveillance in our society today, especially in the context of legal regulation or legal reform, we ought to be careful before making statements about what people supposedly consent to.</p>
                                  <p>Just because Facebook is popular, it doesn't mean Facebook users are actually aware and agree to their practices. Thus, assuming that people are ready to “trade-off” some of their freedom from surveillance in exchange for liking and commenting on pictures, is a very big assumption to make about how people value their privacy and their rights.</p>
                                  <p>Quite to the contrary, I would say we have very little idea in general about what's happening to our rights online and how we're <a href="http://blogs.fsfe.org/hugo/2013/05/whos-tracking-me-online-the-most-google-or-facebook/">being tracked</a>. Hopefully, ToS;DR can fix some of that.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
</channel>
</rss>

